A Guide to the The Records of the Speech & Drama Department in the University Archives Virginia Union University, 1934-1993
Archives and Special Collections Department, L. Douglas Wilder Library, Virginia Union University
Archives and Special Collections Department, L. Douglas Wilder Library, Virginia Union University
The Records of the Speech & Drama Department in the University Archives Virginia Union University, 1934-1993
Archives and Special Collections Department, L. Douglas Wilder Library, Virginia Union University
AR-0003
2 boxes; 1 oversize folder
Speech and Drama Department, Virginia Union University; University Players
Administrative Information
Conditions Governing Access
The collection is open for research use.
Rights Statement for Archival Description
Guide to the Speech & Drama Department, L. Douglas Wilder Library, Virginia Union University is licensed under a [Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial-NoDerivatives 4.0 International License](https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/).
Administrative History
Classes in acting and directing or stagecraft were offered through the English Department until 1975 when the degree of Bachelor of Arts in Speech and Drama was first offered. The University Players began as an extracurricular club that performed in La Cave, the theatre in the basement of Martin E. Gray Hall. Now a part of the department’s curriculum, it is one of the oldest organizations on campus and one of the oldest theatre groups in Richmond. It was the first Richmond theatre group to sponsor a Black drama playwriting contest. The group has performed not only on campus, but throughout the community, and in the 1970's introduced African American drama to areas of Minnesota through a federal program of cultural exchange.
Scope and Content
These records reflect the performances and activities of the Speech and Drama Department at Virginia Union University. The bulk of the collection is performance programs and photographs of the University Players. The Administrative file contains very limited correspondence (mostly congratulatory letters) and press releases.
Arrangement
The Programs and Photographs files are arranged chronologically by performance date.
Adjunct Descriptive Data
Related Archival Materials
Fine Arts Festival (AR-004)
Separated Materials
Photographs (housed in PAR-003)
Broadsides (housed in OAR-003)
Index Terms
Corporate Names:
Speech and Drama Department; University Players; Virginia Union University (Richmond, Va.)
Contents List
- (Box 1)
  - Administrative, 1934-1980
  - Broadsides, Housed in OAR-003
  - University Players
    - Photographs, The Triumph of Job, March 1967
      Housed in PAR-003
    - Photographs, Shadows in Passing or The Big Black Box, April 1967
    - Photographs, God's Trombones, November 1967
    - Photographs, The Chairs & Holocaust, March 1968
    - Photographs, The Fantasticks, April 1968
    - Photographs, A Midwinter's Phantasy, December 1968
    - Photographs, Spoon River Anthology, April 1969
    - Photographs, Slow Dance on the Killing Ground, September 1969
    - Photographs, Black...Out!, October 1969
    - Photographs, To Be Black, October 1970
    - Photographs, The Unwicked Witch, March 1971
    - Photographs, Happy Ending & Day of Absence, November 1971
    - Photographs, This I Believe, March 1972
    - Photographs, Dark of the Moon, November 1972
    - Photographs, Androcles and the Lion, February 1973
    - Photographs, Mind Dream, April 1973
    - Photographs, Sty of the Blind Pig, February 1974
    - Photographs, Highway 1 - USA, April 1974
    - Photographs, Ceremonies in Dark Old Men, October 1974
    - Photographs, Lumpkin's Jail, April 1975
    - Photographs, Undated Programs, 1924, 1932, 1938-1940
    - Programs, 1966-1969
    - Programs, 1969-1971
    - Programs, 1971-1973
    - Programs, 1973-1975
    - Programs, 1975-1977
    - Programs, 1983, 1985, 1991-199
    - Programs, 1998-
    - Programs, Undated
    - Scripts, Freedom
    - Scripts, Lumpkin's Jail
    - Scripts, Mind Dream